<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0"><channel><title><![CDATA[Roobyz Ramblings]]></title><description><![CDATA[A responsive site for sharing thoughts and lessons learned on data science, programming, and technology.]]></description><link>https://roobyz.github.io</link><image><url>/images/background.jpg</url><title>Roobyz Ramblings</title><link>https://roobyz.github.io</link></image><generator>RSS for Node</generator><lastBuildDate>Sun, 16 Apr 2017 22:29:30 GMT</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://roobyz.github.io/rss/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><ttl>60</ttl><item><title><![CDATA[Titanic: Learning Data Science with RStudio]]></title><description><![CDATA[<div id="preamble">
<div class="sectionbody">
<div class="paragraph">
<p>So we are aspiring data scientists and want to dip our toes into <a href="http://rmarkdown.rstudio.com/">RStudio</a>. How do we get started? We dive into the into the waters of the <a href="https://www.kaggle.com/c/titanic">Kaggle Titanic "Competition"</a>, of course!</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>Our objective:</p>
</div>
<div class="ulist">
<ul>
<li>
<p>learn how to think about the competition from a data science perspective</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>predict whether or not a passenger would survive the sinking of the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/RMS_Titanic">RMS Titanic</a></p>
</li>
<li>
<p>enter a Kaggle submission file for evaluation</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>profit!</p>
</li>
</ul>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<div class="sect1">
<h2 id="_kaggle_basics">Kaggle Basics</h2>
<div class="sectionbody">
<div class="paragraph">
<p>Kaggle is a community of data scientists and a platform for facilitating data science journeys. One way to participate, is by entering data science competitions. Similar to other competitions, Kaggle provides two Titanic datasets containing passenger attributes:</p>
</div>
<div class="ulist">
<ul>
<li>
<p>a <em>training set</em>, complete with the outcome (target) variable for training our predictive model(s)</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>a <em>test set</em>, for predicting the unknown outcome variable based on the passenger attributes provided in both datasets.</p>
</li>
</ul>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>After training and validating our predictive model(s), we then enter the submission file to Kaggle for evaluation. As we iterate, we can see the progress we make on the leaderboard.</p>
</div>
<div class="admonitionblock note">
<table>
<tr>
<td class="icon">
<i class="fa icon-note" title="Note"></i>
</td>
<td class="content">
<div class="title"><strong>Thinking like a Data Scientist</strong></div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>We need to use the provided attributes (variables) to train a predictive model, but how does that work? Some variables are correlated with each other. When those variables vary, the correlated variables will also vary to some degree. We need to:</p>
</div>
<div class="ulist">
<ul>
<li>
<p>maximize the number of explanatory variables: those that are correlated with the outcome variable, and</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>minimize the correlation of explanatory variables to each other (<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Multicollinearity">multicollinearity</a>).</p>
</li>
</ul>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>In other words, we need to find the fewest quantity of variables that can explain everything that is going on with the outcome that we want to predict.</p>
</div>
</td>
</tr>
</table>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<div class="sect1">
<h2 id="_titanic_history_lesson">Titanic History Lesson</h2>
<div class="sectionbody">
<div class="paragraph">
<p>The Titanic was a British passenger liner that sank after colliding with an iceberg in the Atlantic on its maiden voyage en route to New York City. It was the largest ship of its time with 10 decks, 8 of which were for passengers.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>There were 2,224 passengers and crew aboard. Of the 1,317 passengers, there were: 324 in First Class (including some of the wealthiest people of the time), 284 in Second Class, and 709 in Third Class. Of these, 869 (66%) were male and 447 (34%) female. There were 107 children aboard, the largest number of which were in Third Class.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>The ship had enough lifeboats for about 1,100 passengers, and more than 1,500 died. Due to the "women and children first" protocol, men were disproportionately left aboard. Also, not all lifeboats were completely filled during the evacuation. The 705 surviving passengers were rescued by the RMS Carpathia around 2 hours after the catastrophe.</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<div class="sect1">
<h2 id="_tutorial_approach">Tutorial Approach</h2>
<div class="sectionbody">
<div class="paragraph">
<p>We&#8217;ll approach this project in multiple parts. This is still a work in progress, but roughly speaking it should look like:</p>
</div>
<div class="olist arabic">
<ol class="arabic">
<li>
<p>Part 1: Basic Setup</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Part 2: Feature Engineering</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Part 3: Prediction</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Part 4: Conclusion</p>
</li>
</ol>
</div>
</div>
</div>]]></description><link>https://roobyz.github.io/2017/04/16/Predict-Survival-Propensity-of-Titanic-Passengers.html</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://roobyz.github.io/2017/04/16/Predict-Survival-Propensity-of-Titanic-Passengers.html</guid><category><![CDATA[Blog]]></category><category><![CDATA[Open_Source]]></category><category><![CDATA[Machine_Learning]]></category><category><![CDATA[Analytics]]></category><category><![CDATA[Data_Science]]></category><dc:creator><![CDATA[Roberto Rivera]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Sun, 16 Apr 2017 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Qualitative Prediction of Weight-Lifting Exercises]]></title><description><![CDATA[<div class="paragraph">
<p>One day your company tells your team that they should switch from a proprietary analytics platform like <a href="https://www.sas.com/">SAS</a>, to something <a href="https://opensource.org/">open source</a> like <a href="http://rmarkdown.rstudio.com/">RStudio</a>. Undoubtedly some analysts may become fascinated, while others anxious. How would you get them excited about the switch?</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>My approach was to demonstrate the potential of the new open source platform. How easily could RStudio generate reproducible research and facilitate story telling with data? How could we weave together narrative text and code to seamlessly produce and deliver elegantly formatted analyses to multiple audiences?</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>Leveraging Human Activity Recognition (HAR) data provided from a <a href="http://groupware.les.inf.puc-rio.br/har#ixzz3de67BWZU">Groupware@LES</a> study, a machine learning use-case was born. HAR data has become ubiquitous with the advent of devices like the Fitbit, Nike FuelBand, and even smartphones. Although users of these devices tend to quantify how much they participate in an activity, they rarely consider how <em>well</em> they perform the activity.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>The provided multiclass variable was generated by participants wearing HAR devices, and is relatively balanced (equally distributed). This simplifies the analysis somewhat since we don&#8217;t need to consider tactics to combat <a href="http://machinelearningmastery.com/tactics-to-combat-imbalanced-classes-in-your-machine-learning-dataset/">imbalanced classes</a>. In addition, this lets us focus primarily on the other major analytics steps required in most machine learning projects.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>Machine learning project goals:</p>
</div>
<div class="ulist">
<ul>
<li>
<p>use the multiclass variable to build a predictor that distinguishes between participants that correctly completed fitness exercises versus those that hadn’t and what their mistakes may have been.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>demonstrate the feasibility of using RStudio for delivering reproducible research via a webpage.</p>
</li>
</ul>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>The <a href="https://cdn.rawgit.com/roobyz/PredictiveML/c0297e0d771e39633436b3cff87707f0c5f4b851/ml_activity_success.html">project results</a>, and <a href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/roobyz/PredictiveML/master/ml_activity_success.Rmd">code</a> are available on my <a href="https://github.com/roobyz/PredictiveML">GitHub Repository</a>.</p>
</div>]]></description><link>https://roobyz.github.io/2017/04/15/Identifying-the-Successful-Completion-of-Weight-Lifting-Exercises.html</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://roobyz.github.io/2017/04/15/Identifying-the-Successful-Completion-of-Weight-Lifting-Exercises.html</guid><category><![CDATA[Blog]]></category><category><![CDATA[Open_Source]]></category><category><![CDATA[Machine_Learning]]></category><category><![CDATA[Analytics]]></category><category><![CDATA[Data_Science]]></category><dc:creator><![CDATA[Roberto Rivera]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 15 Apr 2017 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>