<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0"><channel><title><![CDATA[Roobyz Ramblings]]></title><description><![CDATA[A responsive site for sharing thoughts and lessons learned on data science, programming, and technology.]]></description><link>https://roobyz.github.io</link><generator>RSS for Node</generator><lastBuildDate>Sat, 15 Apr 2017 19:46:14 GMT</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://roobyz.github.io/rss/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><ttl>60</ttl><item><title><![CDATA[Qualitative Completion of Weight-Lifting Exercises]]></title><description><![CDATA[<div class="paragraph">
<p>One day your company tells your team that they should switch from a proprietary analytics platform like <a href="https://www.sas.com/">SAS</a>, to something open source like <a href="http://rmarkdown.rstudio.com/">RStudio</a>. Undoubtedly some analysts may become facinated, while others anxious. How would you get people excited about the switch?</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>Demonstrate the potential of the new platform, right? How easily could RStudio generate reproducible research and facilitate story telling with data? How could we weave together narrative text and code to seamlessly produce and deliver elegantly formatted analyses to multiple audiences?</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>Leveraging Human Activity Recognition (HAR) data provided from a <a href="http://groupware.les.inf.puc-rio.br/har#ixzz3de67BWZU">Groupware@LES</a> study, a machine learning use-case was born. HAR data has become ubiquitous with the advent of devices like the Fitbit, Nike FuelBand, and even smartphones. Although users of these devices tend to quantify how much they participate in an activity, they rarely consider how <em>well</em> they perform the activity.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>This machine learning exercise is "simple" in the sense that our data is well balanced across the class variables. This saves us from needing to account for that. However, there is ample opportunity to demonstrate the other major analytics steps required in most machine learning projects.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>The machine learning goal: can we distinguish between participants in a fitness experiment, that have correctly completed fitness exercises versus those that haven’t and what mistakes were made, if any? We will assess how accurately we can classify the exercises performed by non-participants solely based on their HAR data.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>The <a href="https://cdn.rawgit.com/roobyz/PredictiveML/c0297e0d771e39633436b3cff87707f0c5f4b851/ml_activity_success.html">Project Results</a>, and code are available on my <a href="https://github.com/roobyz/PredictiveML">GitHub Repository</a>.</p>
</div>]]></description><link>https://roobyz.github.io/2017/04/15/Identifying-the-Successful-Completion-of-Weight-Lifting-Exercises.html</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://roobyz.github.io/2017/04/15/Identifying-the-Successful-Completion-of-Weight-Lifting-Exercises.html</guid><category><![CDATA[Blog]]></category><category><![CDATA[Open_Source]]></category><category><![CDATA[Machine_Learning]]></category><category><![CDATA[Analytics]]></category><dc:creator><![CDATA[Roberto Rivera]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 15 Apr 2017 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>