<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0"><channel><title><![CDATA[Roobyz Ramblings]]></title><description><![CDATA[A responsive site for sharing thoughts and lessons on data science, programming, and technology.]]></description><link>https://roobyz.github.io</link><generator>RSS for Node</generator><lastBuildDate>Sat, 15 Apr 2017 17:18:48 GMT</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://roobyz.github.io/rss/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><ttl>60</ttl><item><title><![CDATA[Identifying the Successful Completion of Weight-Lifting Exercises]]></title><description><![CDATA[<div class="paragraph">
<p>One day your company tells you that the analytics team should switch from a proprietary platform like SAS, to something open source like RStudio. Undoubtedly some analysts may feel excited, while others a bit anxious. How would you get people excited about the potential switch?</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>My approach was to demonstrate the potential of the new platform. How can we use RStudio to generate reproducible research, and facilitate story telling with data? How could we weave together narrative text and code to seamlessly produce elegantly formatted analysis to multiple audiences?</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>Leveraging Human Activity Recognition (HAR) data provided from a Groupware@LES study, a machine learning project was born. HAR data has become ubiquitous with the advent of devices like the Fitbit, Nike FuelBand, and even smartphones. Although users of these devices tend to quantify how much they participate in an activity, they rarely consider how <em>well</em> they perform the activity.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>This machine learning exercise is a "toy" project in the sense that the Groupware@LES data is well balanced across the class variables. This saves us from needing to account for that, however provides ample opportunity to do all of the other major data wrangling and analytics steps required in most projects.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>The machine learning goal: can we distinguish between participants in a fitness experiment, that have correctly completed fitness exercises versus those that haven’t and what mistakes were made, if any? We will assess how accurately we can classify the exercises performed by non-participants solely based on their HAR data.</p>
</div>]]></description><link>https://roobyz.github.io/2017/04/15/Identifying-the-Successful-Completion-of-Weight-Lifting-Exercises.html</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://roobyz.github.io/2017/04/15/Identifying-the-Successful-Completion-of-Weight-Lifting-Exercises.html</guid><category><![CDATA[Blog]]></category><category><![CDATA[Open_Source]]></category><category><![CDATA[Machine_Learning]]></category><dc:creator><![CDATA[Roberto Rivera]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 15 Apr 2017 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>